under Stalin, an industry was created;
при Сталине была создана промышленность
food cards were abolished in
продуктовые карточки были отменены в
1947; for
сорок седьмом году для
comparison, in enlightened Western Europe
сравнения в просвещенной Западной Европе
they were abolished only in the early
они были отменены только в начале
sixties; food cards; yes, the
шестидесятых продуктовые карточки да
USSR was the undisputed leader by
СССР была безусловным лидером к
1953 in all
пятьдесят третьему году во всех
areas. I remember exactly the
областях Я точно помню
tanks coming in. Listen, you respect Stalin
танки входили Слушай ты Сталина уважаешь
Yes  and then when the abyss
Да а тыж потом когда хляб
In what year is it fifty-six?
В каком году пя шем пятьдесят шестой Да
Yes, now for
так сейчас
a second there are tanks in Budapest for sure yes
секунду танки в Будапеште точно да
yes 1 9  5
да 1 9 5
6 Hungarian
6 венгерское
Uprising Yes fifty-sixth
Восстание Да пятьдесят шестой
year
год
P6 November 11
П6 11 ноября
October 23 October 11 So well, this is
23 октября 11 ноября Так ну это
Wikipedia Wikipedia is about the
Википедия Википедия - это про
resource, it
ресурс
means everything Naru Naru
значит всё Нару Нару
Naru so Bush Well, well, fifty-six is
Нару так Буш Ну хорошо пятьдесят шестой
good, but I
хорошо а вот
wonder why in p Stalin has already
интересно А почему в п Сталин уже как 3
been dead for 3 years  fifty-sixth Stalin died at 3
умер в пятьдесят шестом Сталин как 3
years ago Yes because he died 3 years
года умер Да потому что он умер 3 года
ago see Stalin at 3 years old Died yes A
назад смотри Сталин как 3 года Умер да А
at 56  year in Budapest they raised an Uprising
в 56 году в Будапеште подняли Восстание
But I wonder what they raised
А вот интересно против чего они подняли
an Uprising against Soviet power
Восстание против Советской власти
against and Soviet power, which was at that
у а Советская власть какая была на то
time
время
already Stalin’s
уже Сталинская
occupation occupation Absolutely
оккупационная оккупационная Совершенно
right, and this occupation was the
верно причём эту оккупацию
Nazi officers who released
гитлеровские офицеры которых выпустили
raisins in the GDR yes And in this year
изюм в ГДР да А в п сем году в Москву
they came to Moscow  Tamanskaya and Kantemirovskaya Divisions
зашла Таманская и Кантемировская Дивизии
led by Marshal
во главе с маршалом
Zhukov, tell me something wrong  and Well, I
жуковым что-то не так расскажи и Ну я
see doubt on TM Yes, you are a very
вижу сомнение на ТМ ли Да Ты очень
wonderful psychologist, tell the division in the
замечательный психолог скажи дивизия в
fifty-seventh Moscow and well, there
пятьдесят седьмом Москву и ну и
was a coup d'etat And in the
произошёл государственный переворот А в
fifty-seventh year, to replace
пятьдесят седьмом году на смену
the Constitution of the thirty-sixth year,
Конституции тридцать шестого года
which was recognized by the whole world and the USSR was
которую признал весь мир и СССР был
legitimate From the thirty-sixth year to the
легитимным С тридцать шестого года до
fifty  on
пятьдесят
the seventh, yes, yes, it was legitimate since the beginning of
седьмого да да он был легитимным с рише
the year, the USSR was recognized by all world
года СССР признали все мировые
powers. So what, they changed
державы Так а что что там изменили
the Constitution in fifty-
Конституцию в пятьдесят
seven, the leading role of
седьмом ведущая роль
the party  the leading role of the party And before that,
партии ведущая роль партии А до этого
then they began then they began to destroy
потом стали потом стали уничтожать
private business 40% of the Stalinist economy
частный бизнес 40% сталинской экономики
- this is a frequent business artels cooperatives
- это частый бизнес артели кооперативы
cooperative
кооперативное
association
объединение
Think about private business under Stalin Yes,
Прикинь частный бизнес при Сталине Да
Stalin had a lot of private business,
массо Сталине был частный бизнес
imagine a massive one, I understood
представляешь массовый понял
So well, artels were there Yeah So and then the
Так ну артели были были Угу Так а дальше
collective farm  the same artel is only an
колхоз та же самая артель только
Agricultural artel. Listen,
Сельскохозяйственная артель Слушай а
the question is interesting to me, but in the fifth and
вопрос вот мне такое интересно да в пят
seventh year Zhukov started the Tamansk and
седьмом году Жуков завёл Таманской и
Kantemirovskaya division to Moscow and
Кантемировской дивизию в Москву и
made a coup with whom they exchanged for whom
сделали переворот кого на кого поменяли
in the leadership of the USSR Khru was approved for the
в руководстве СССР хру утвердили на
position of this general secretary. And
должность этого генерального секретаря А
before that, who was the general
до этого кто был генеральным
secretaries before that was Stalin about Stalin
секретарям до этого был Сталин о Сталин
then Stalin died they installed Khrushchev
потом Сталин умер поставили Хрущёва
then by the forces of the Comintern in the fifty-
потом силами Коминтерна в пятьдесят
seventh year of this same Khrushchev from  the
седьмом году этого самого Хрущёва от
authorities
власти
remove and after the introduction of the Taman
отстраняют и после ввода Таманской
Division this Khrushchev back to the
Дивизии этого Хрущёва обратно уже на
throne, in fact, they return Uh-huh, good,
трон по сути дела возвращают Угу хорошо
and that’s it  already another USSR, we don’t
а и это уже другой СССР мы ничего не
know anything about the history of our country for
знаем об истории нашей страны за
the thirties, forties, fifties and
тридцатые сороковые пятидесятые и
sixties. And these are the most interesting
шестидесятые годы А это самые интересные
years question question question I
года вопрос вопрос вопрос я правильно
understand correctly that some
понимаю что какой-то
Comintern was in
Коминтерн был в
Come on, Communist stop The
Да ну Коммунистический стоп
Communist International is an
Коммунистический Интернационал - это
international
международная
organization with the headquarters of the Comintern in
организация штаб квартира коментерна в
that time in London was actually once
то время в Лондоне находилась вообще-то
again how the Comintern removed
ещё раз то как Коминтерн убрал
Khrushchev Well, with the help of their supporters in the
Хрущёва Ну силами своих сторонников в
central committee And how they
центральном комитете А как они его
removed him, voting there with some of their
убрали голосования там какими-то своими
movements
движениями
nevertheless, a fact is a fact, the ruv was relative
тем не менее Факт есть факт рув был отн
from what it should be and who who stood instead of him
от свое должно и кто кто вместо него
so
стал так
he was very quickly returned to his
тот его очень быстренько вернули на
place Well, what
место Ну вот
happened in p this year is correct,
вот происходило в п сем году правильно
look, listen, I understand, I’m
вот смотри слушай я понимаю я тебе
now telling you things that are very
сейчас рассказываю вещи которые очень
difficult to understand
трудны для понимания
really, look I’m a good student Yes,
напря что да смотри Я хороший ученик Да
I just want to just understand
я хочу просто хочу просто понять
the chronology, look Khrushchev was after
хронологию смотри Хрущёв был после
Stalin Yes, the leader of the USSR in
Сталина Да руководитель СССР в пятьдесят
1957, some Comintern
седьмом году какой-то Коминтерн его
removed him and then  Zhukov returned him then the
отстранил и потом Жуков его вернул то
Comintern was then a very influential
Коминтерн тогда был весьма влиятельной
organization Yes, but how much he was
организацией Да но насколько его
suspended how much he was suspended
отстранили сколько он был отстранён
minute day month Well there for several days
минуту день месяц Ну там несколько дней
several days Who Who led the USSR
несколько дней Кто Кто руководил СССР
these few days Who
эти несколько дней Кто
was there the issue of a coup d'etat was being decided
был там решался вопрос о Государственном
these days it's like in the ninety  the
перевороте в эти дни это как В девяносто
first State Emergency Committee how long it lasted 3 days
первом гкчп сколько оно длилось 3 дня
who is Who led the country from
кто вот Кто руководил страной с 19
August 19 to the twenty-first
августа по двадцать первое
And the question for
А вопрос
experts is
знатокам тоже
the same Yes, I also understood that tanks were brought into
самое Да понял также танки ввели в
Moscow Yeah, it turns out  In ninety-
Москву Угу то получается В девяносто
three, they also brought tanks into Moscow,
третьем также ввели танки в Москву так
so I understand correctly that as a result of the
то я правильно понимаю что в результате
military coup in the USSR in 1957,
военного переворота в СССР в 1957 году
Khrushchev was changed to
Хрущёва поменяли на
Khrushchev, Krushov was returned to his
Хрущёва крушова вернули на своё
place in his rightful place, they changed it
место на законное место поменяли это
when another person was installed instead of Khrushchev,
когда вместо Хрущёва другого человека
wait, then Khrushchev is illegal
ли то подожди то Хрущёва незаконно
suspended or illegally returned why
отстранили или незаконно вернули почему
he was illegally returned but legally
его незаконно вернули но законно
suspended understood And who will remove him
отстранили понял А кто его отстранят
What kind of
Какие
figures are supporters of the Stalinist USSR?
деятели сторонники сталинского СССР
Yeah, you understand the revolution, who did it in the
Ага ты пойми революцию то Кто делал в
seventeenth year and all sorts of peasants
семнадцатом году а всякая крестьяне что
or workers German Agent
ли рабочие немецкий Агент
on their bayonets Latvian riflemen and under the
на их штыках латышские стрелки да под
guise of German officers Yes but who
видом там немецких офицеров Да но кто
managed all this
управлял
London London in London there
Лондон Лондон в Лондоне
was the second congress of
было второй съезд
the All-Russian Communist Party of Belarus All-Russian Russian
вкпб Всероссийская Российская
Communist Party of the Bolsheviks
Коммунистическая партия Большевиков
Yes, where was the split into Bolsheviks and
Да где был раскол на Большевиков и
Mensheviks, Mensheviks,
меньшевиков меньшевиков да
and why? They were called Bolsheviks and
а почему Их назвали большевики и
Mensheviks.
меньшевики
number of people in the faction No, don’t
А по количеству людей Во фракции Нет не
let me say no, the Bolsheviks expressed
давай говори нет большевики выражали
the interests of the majority of the majority And the
интересы большинства большинства А
Mensheviks are noblewomen, how come they are
меньшевики дворянки ну как же так нас
depriving us of our rights? Is it that this worker
лишают прав Это что же вот этот рабочий
has as many rights as I have in my
у него прав столько же сколько у меня
yard nena you
дворе нена вы
we will fight against this and a
мы воевать будем против этого ну и
civil war  As a
гражданскую войну получили в
result, we got the formation of such a
итоге становление такого
state, then in the fifth and seventh year
государства то в пят седьмом году
Khrushchev was illegally returned in a couple of days,
Хрущёва незаконно вернули за пару дней
it was already an illegal state.
это было уже незаконное государство
Sorry for interrupting, but you
Извини что перебил но ты абсолютно
said absolutely correctly. Maybe with irony, maybe
правильно сказал Может с иронией может
without  Irony But that’s exactly how it was already an
без Иронии Но именно так это было уже
illegal state,
незаконное государство
these are the decisions of the decree, and so
вот эти решения постановления и так
on. It was the decision of the decree of the
далее Это было решение постановление
illegal state. The Soviet Union
незаконного государства Советский Союз
was generally a legal state, and then there was
был вообще законным государством а ещ
China. Why didn’t anyone
был такой Китай А почему Китай никто не
consider China as a red threat? Never
рассматривал как красную угрозу никогда
thought about it. No. It’s interesting, but there
не задумывался нет Интересно а ведь там
there was also communism, and their
же тоже был коммунизм причём у них
Constitution is still an exact copy of the
Конституция до сих пор точна копия нй
Constitution, the monuments to Stalin stand.
Конституции памятники Сталину стоят В
In what year did China become
како в каком году Китай стал
communist in 1949 when
коммунистическим в сорок девятом когда
no, so there not only in 4 in the same place it
нет так там не только в 4 там же короче
was shorter  The battle between the Republic of China,
была Заруба между республикой Китай
which is the true China of Medan, or
который истинный Китай медано ский или
how it was and Dadada there in Taiwan, and
как он был да дадада там на Тайване и
Continental China still
Континентальный Китай всё раз до сих пор
remains, yes, that is, that is, roughly
Да остался да да то есть то есть грубо
speaking, the nobles of China sailed to Taiwan,
говоря дворяне Китая уплыли На Тайвань
so naturally America took them under the wing
вот их естественно под крыло взяла
Well, by the way  a good result
Америка Ну кстати неплохой результат
was obtained tsmc plant for example in Taiwan
получился tsmc завод например на Тайване
Leader And this is How do you look at what is
Лидер А вот такое Как ты смотришь что
there where for example Taiwan and such
там где вот например Тайвань и такой
China in Taiwan the standard of living
Китай на Тайване выше уровень жизни
technology is higher  and so on, yes South Korea and
технологии и так дальше да Южная Корея и
North Korea where there is capitalism there is
Северная Корея там где капитализм там
movement there where communes are significant in
движуха там где коммуни отно значно в
North Korea It’s worse I wouldn’t wish my enemy to
Северной Корея хуже я врагу не пожелаю
live in North Korea
жить в Северной Корее
here What are we even talking about like this How does
тут О чём вообще разговаривать так Как
this happen everywhere the hand touches
так получается всюду куда трогает рука
This is the former Sovka
Вот это бывшего Совка
everywhere  What a scoop again
всюду а Совка какого опять
And the one that appeared at the seam and then
А тот который при шве возник и дальше
began to develop to the point of
стал развиваться поч развиваться о
rotting and then in the next year they announced that there would be
гнить а потом в Деном году объявили чтоб
no SS But now we are the masters here so
СС нет А вот теперь мы тут хозяева так
one hundred Well  Look, for the sake of interest,
сто Ну смотри я ради интереса
Slim, now we have neo-feudalism here and
Слим теперь у нас здесь неофеодализм а
who are the feudal lords, look at the Korean War,
кто такие феодалы смотри корейская война
I’m deliberately
я специально
naked, I’m deliberately fattening up when the Korean
нагу я специально нагул когда корейская
War, so as not to be mistaken, it still
война чтобы не ошибиться она всё-таки
happened under Stalin in 1950 PT. That is, under
была при Сталине 1950 ПТ год То есть при
Stalin, yes. That’s how it turns out, Stalin
Сталине да Так это получается Сталин
supported Yes  this war, yes. And what
поддерживал Да вот эту войну да А он что
if Stalin knew what the North is currently
если бы Сталин знал то что сейчас Север
doing in North Korea? Where in the whole
в Северной Корее происходит Где на всю
country there is only one fat man,
страну только один толстячок есть вот
this Kim Chin? Yes, he is in  I would have
этот Ким чин Да он в горбу бы
rolled over my hump. So in the USSR there was also
перевернулся Так а в СССР также было на
only one Stalin in the whole country,
всю страну один Сталин один Сталин
fat Stalin yes Well, look, everything is like in the USSR
толстячок да Ну смотри всё как в СССР
Stalin has kimchi here Yes In short, here in his memory
Сталин тут кимчи Да Короче тут ему памя
everyone else lived in poverty yes Yes
все остальные в нищете жили да Да
Seriously Seriously yes yes Oh Lord,
Серьёзно Серьёзно да да О Господи ну
look full of full cosplay  like
смотри полны полный косплей типа
North Korea is also a Dictator
Северной Кореи тоже тый Диктатор
and we have a complete cosplay of North Korea
да полный косплей Северной Кореи мы
today and God forbid we live under
сегодня и не дай Бог нам прожить при
this regime for more years So explain  explain
этом режиме Ещё лет Так обясни объясни
what is the difference between a hundred years later, so
чем отличается ста чере лет так
Stalin’s dog is different from kimchi,
псе Сталин от кимчи
how is it different?
этого чем он отличается
Yes, under Stalin, an industry was created;
Да при Сталине была создана
food cards were
промышленность продуктовые карточки были
abolished in 1947; for
отменены в сорок седьмом году для
comparison, in enlightened Western Europe
сравнения в просвещенной Западной Европе
they were abolished only in the early
они были отменены только в начале
sixties; food cards; yes, the
шестидесятых продуктовые карточки да
USSR was the undisputed leader in
СССР была безусловным лидером к
fifty-third year in all areas
пятьдесят третьему году во всех областях
Electronics astronautics Science and so
Электроника космонавтика Наука и так
on I graduated from the Ural
дальше я закончил упи Уральский
Polytechnic Institute, it’s obvious you
политехнический институт это видно ты
know when it was founded No at
знаешь когда он был основан Нет при
Stalin, probably in the twenty-first year,
Сталине наверное в двадцать первом году
it was founded under Stalin,
он был основан при Сталине были
the chemistry department and the radio department and the construction department were built, well, the department is the
построены химфак и радиофак и стройфак
faculty. Come on, without these
ну фак факультет Да давай без этих у
you don’t have an American flag. Yes, phage is a faculty.
тебя нет американского флага Да фаг -
Yes, I graduated from the faculty. I
это факультет Да факультет вот я
graduated from Electrical Engineering. I saw laboratories that
закончил Я видел лаборатории которые
were built in the thirties.  at the
были в тридцатые годы построены на
Faculty of Electrical Engineering
электротехническом факультете
Yes, just Google the pictures, now you
Да просто вот загугли картинки он сейчас
know it’s now called UrFU UrFU
знаешь он сейчас называется УрФУ УрФУ
Ural Federal University for some reason it was
Уральский федеральный университет его за
merged with  a university for the humanities,
объединили с гуманитарным университетом
well, that’s basically all that’s happening now
ну это вообще всё что происходит сейчас
in my country It’s just how not to
в моей стране Это просто как тут не
drink here That’s how, looking at all this,
бухать Вот как вот глядя вот на всё вот
this is just
это вот это просто
possible Listen, what if Stalin was so
можно Слушай а если Сталин был такой
good Why did he attack Finland in
хороший Зачем он напал на Финляндию в
1939 attacked Finland yes  about the
девятом напал на Финляндию да про
Finnish war, I haven’t studied this question
финскую войну я вопрос этот не изучал
Yeah, I don’t know why, but I
Ага А почему не знаю но у меня времени
just
просто
don’t have time. Okay, I’ll heed your advice.
нет Хорошо я я внемлю твоему совету
Maybe we’ll meet
Может быть мы когда-нибудь встретимся
here again, chat roulette, but  I have
здесь чат рулетке снова и но у меня
free time, you won’t think that I’m
свободное время ты не подумаешь что я
there It’s just that I
там Просто у меня времени свободного на
really don’t have much free time. I understand, I believe, I
самом деле мало Я понимаю я верю верю я
don’t think anything bad about you, not
не подумал ничего плохого про тебя нетча
at Roulette. I only go out for about three
в Рулетку Я выхожу всего Часа на три
hours before bed.
пере перед сном Вот
That’s if I have time.  And by the way,
вот если у меня найдётся время А кстати
here on New Year’s holidays I might
тут ну в новогодние праздники Я может
take an interest in this
поинтересуюсь этим
PTO This is the Finnish war, if I’m not
ВОМ Вот это финская война это если я не
mistaken it’s the year thirty-nine yes
ошибаюсь тридцать девятый год да
yes Well, first I would like to hear
да Ну хорошо я бы хотел услышать для
your interpretation of the text I’m
начала твою интерпретацию текста мне мне
interested I want to understand  why do I
интересно Я хочу понять почему я так
think that Stalin the aggressor attacked
смотрю что Сталин агрессор напал на
Finland?
Финляндию
Stalin the aggressor attacked Finland.
Сталин агрессор напал на Финляндию А
Why did Stalin attack
зачем Сталин напал на
Romania? I have no idea,
Румынию Понятия не
but
имею а на
I’m talking about Poland.
Польшу я же говорю Понятия не
I have no idea. I’ll take up these questions. I
имею Я этими вопросами займусь я
started to be interested in history. Why
историей начал интересоваться Зачем
did Stalin destroy his
Сталин уничтожал свой
people, his people,
народ свой народ
seriously? Yes  the maximum profit of the population
серьёзно Да прибыль населения
was under Stalin. I wonder
максимальная была при Сталине Интересно
how he destroyed his people like that. The
как это он так уничтожал свой народ
maximum profit was even under the
максимальная прибыль была ещё при
empire, there were 12 children per family under the
империи там по 12 детей было в семье при
empire. Yes Who  of these 12 children lived to
империи Да Кто из этих 12 детей доживал
at least 20 4-5 lived like this even under
хотя бы до 20 4-5 доживали так и при
Stalin 4-5 seriously Yes look The point is
Сталине 4-5 серьёзно Да смотри Дело в
that Bulgakov succeeds in
том что получается у Булгакова у
Bulgakov look at the question of reproduction -
Булгакова смотри вопрос размножения -
This is a question of formation Yes, for example,
Это вопрос формации Да например
industrial formations no longer reproduce in the same way
индустриальные формации уже не так типа
because  agrarian
размножаются потому что аграрная
formation Yes, it’s traditional there It multiplies
формация Да там традиционно Там множится
and so on in the cities People no longer have
и так дальше в городах Люди уже не имеют
10-20 children and so on you tell me
по 10-20 детей и так дальше ты мне скажи
yes Stalin killed people or
да Сталин убил людей или
not If someone st then what's the matter and what's the
нет Если кого-то ул то за дело а что за
matter a million people who were repressed was
дело миллион людей репрессированных было
it all for the cause a million people
это все за дело миллион людей
a million people seriously Yes in Russia there are 4 million
миллион людей серьёзно Да в России 4 млн
policemen
полицаев
and
и
And that's not counting the rest and And what do you
И это не считая остальных и И как ты
think about  they need to be done listen
думаешь что с ними надо делать слушай
This is a question that shouldn’t stand 4 million policemen
Такой вопрос не стоять 4 милна полицаев
plus judges
плюс судьи
Prosecutors and
Прокуроры а
what should officials do with them
что с ними делать
here is Toto and it Listen to the question
чиновники вот Тото и оно Слушай вопрос
I have, the point is that I’m
такой у меня де в том что я тут в
running a small chat here on discord Yes, I have
дискорде небольшой чатик веду Да у меня
mine  colleagues, some of them are from America They are
мои коллеги некоторые они из Америки
also watching us here there are a few
Тоже смотрят нас тут там есть немножко
seven people don’t you want
семь человек не хочешь
confirms ameri want to confirm
потверждает амери хочешь потверждает
questions let’s
вопросы
go who will play around I will ban
поехали кто будет баловаться буду банить
like seriously
типа серьёзно
Damon a serious person quite a
дамон серьёзный человек довольно начин
serious question
серьёзный вопрос
Let’s barn asks who and why
Давайте амбар спрашивает кто и почему
leaked
слил
Trotsky Who and why leaked Trotsky
троцкого Кто и почему слил троцкого
Good
Хороший
question Troki was an active participant in
вопрос Троки был активный участник
the revolution
революции
and the Civil War, which ended
и Гражданской войны которая закончилась
in, among other things,
в помимо всего прочего из России были
jewelry, jewelry, gold,
вывезены драгоценности украшения золото
diamonds, etc., were exported from Russia  other other
бриллианты и прочее прочее прочее
yes Well, that means to him in Mexico when
да Ну вот к нему значит в Мексике когда
he lived and in his own person
он жил да в своём особ
with an ax Yes, they came to him and said Hey
топором Да ему приехали и сказали Слышь
Lev, come on, give it all
Лёва давай-ка ты это возвращай всё
back, and he thought that he was in Mexico
обратно а он думал что он в Мексике за
overseas, but he got
океаном но он
them Well, that’s why he got them  an ice pick to
их Ну за что и получил ледорубом по
the head And also Trotsky and
башке А ещё а ещё Троцкий е
Zinoviev saw the leading role of the All-Union Communist Party of Belarus in
Зиновьев видели главенствующую роль
the Union, this is what
вкпб Союзе это то против чего как раз и
Stalin fought against. Yes, you may be
боролся Сталин Да вы можете быть
Bolsheviks, but you are not  have the right to be
большевиками но вы не имейте права быть
neo-feudalism
неофеодализм
people decide everything I understand Let's move on
народ всё решает понял Поехали дальше
That's why he was killed That's why he was killed I
Вот за это его Вот за это его и убили
understand everything so how old are you
понял всё так э сколько тебе лет
Victoria asks eh stand I
спрашивает Виктория э стоять Я на личные
don't answer personal questions Victoria without personal
вопросы не отвечаю Виктория без личных
questions so I
вопросов так
understand Max asks how you feel
бо понял Макс спрашивает как относишься
about
к
Patrushev  Let's go
патрушеву Давай
further,
дальше
eyes Let's go further with the
глазки Давай дальше
book,
книги
no, he was the editor-in-chief of the
писа нет он был главным редактором
newspaper Pravda understood
Газеты Правда понял
so Roman asks how many people
так спрашивает Роман сколько людей
died in the civil
погибло в гражданской
war, the exact numbers are
войне точны цифры
unknown, there
неизвестно
were leaks in the USSR in the forty-sixth forty-seventh years
седьмых годах был
hunger hunger
голод
hunger because the post-war period and
голод потому что послевоенное время и
any hedgehog Where where there was famine, it was not
еже любые Где где и был голод то не по
throughout the USSR
всему СССР
Exactly
Точно
exactly the problem of hunger was generally solved
точно проблему голода вообще решили
after the forty-seventh year, you know why
после сорок седьмого года знаете почему
Dear
Уважаемые слушатели
Discord listeners because after the Yalta
Дискорда потому что после ялтинской
conference of Stalin Roosevelt and
конференции Сталина Рузвельта и
Church, Eastern Europe became our
черче Восточная Европа стала нашей
mandate there  there was a huge
подмандатные туда было ВБ огромное
amount of money from the World Bank, specialist
количество денег сил специалистов
resources, and so on.
ресурсов и так дальше
Agriculture there was just
просто сельское хозяйство было
great, we all remember Hungarian peas,
великолепно вот мы же все помним горошек
and not only
Да и не только
peas
горошек
tomatoes even this one is like his half-horse
помидоры даже этот как его полуконь
half-brother What drink I'm many years old in
полубрат Какой напиток Мне много лет на
fact, but I remember the reputation of the
самом деле но я помню слыв Бряк
Bulgarian Breakfast, this strong drink
болгарский этот крепкий напиток
Sunny Beach is rare rubbish, by
Солнечный берег дрянь редкостная кстати
the way, but nevertheless, the Bulgarian wine
говоря но тем не менее вино болгарское
was Bulgarian tobacco
было Болгар табак
p4
р4
polt, this is what I started smoking when I started smoking
полт это то что я когда начал курить вот
Edo  white with glasses Yes, a pack like that, it
Эдо белая с чки Да пачка такая это ВС
was BC Bulgarian tobacco, and it was excellent tobacco,
был Болгар табак причём отличный табак
I’ll tell you, not just what it is now, but what’s
был скажу я вам не то что сейчас то что
in stores
в магазинах
so I can repeat it, I understand Who is he
чтоб повторять понял А кто такой
Putin that I have already spoken on this topic
Путин что я уже говорил на эту тему
many
много
times
раз
so Yura asks How much did it cost
так Юра спрашивает Сколько в СССР стоила
to deliver
доставка
pizza in the USSR I didn’t know what pizza was in the
пиццы я не знал что такое пицца в
USSR Why did I have pancakes
СССР А почему у меня были оладушки
pancakes belyashiki
блинчики беляшики
bo Arsen asks why Stalin
бо Арсен спрашивает почему Сталин
organized the blockade of Leningrad it wasn’t Stalin who
устроил блокаду Ленинграда это не Сталин
staged the blockade
устроил блокаду
le Stalin  Yeah, of course, bloodthirsty Stalin
ле Сталин Ага конечно кровожадный Сталин
wanted to
хотел уморить
starve a million inhabitants of Leningrad.
голодом миллион жителей Ленинграда Какой
What kind of person was he?
же он был к какой же он был
[music]
[музыка]
bloody, what’s wrong with you?  head in
кровавы что у вас что с головой-то
general
вообще
And I apologize
А я прошу прощения
for asking Who are you according to the
за спрашивают Кто ты по
Zodiac Aquarius Aquarius
Зодиаку Водолей Водолей
Yes, why is there not 22 of us there,
Да почему чтото нас там походу не 22
but they pulled up these
человека а они подтянули этих
relatives there are already 47 in my
родственников там уже уже 47 у меня в
discord Yes, really, Alexa
дискорде Да реально так Алекса
asks why there were always
спрашивает почему были всегда в ССР
closed borders in the USSR  iron curtain o
закрытые границы железный занавес о
Good question who who asked
Хороший вопрос кто кто задал вопрос
Alex's question Alex means look
Алекса Алекса значит смотри
Alex until 1957, the USSR was a free
Алекса до 57 года СССР был свободным
democratic state with elected
демократическим государством с выборными
authorities, police, courts and
органами власти милиции судов и вообще
all government bodies in general  Yes, with open
всех органов управления Да с открытыми
borders, the Iron Curtain over
границами железный занавес над
the USSR, you know when it came down, when and
СССР знаете когда опустился когда и
why in the early
почему в начале
sixties, but because so that none of the
шестидесятых а потому что чтобы никто из
Soviet citizens could see how the
советских граждан не видел как живёт
party Elite lives on the Cote d'Azur of
партийная Элита На лазурном берегу
France. What did you think? Did they just yesterday or
Франции А вы что думали Они только вчера
something? On the Cote d'Azur of France, villas
что ли На лазурном берегу Франции виллы
for themselves  bought and in Italy
себе купили и в Италии нет
no no there was free entry and exit from the SSS, I
нет был свободный въезд и выезд из ССС я
understand correctly that under Stalin people
правильно понимаю что при Сталине люди
could easily leave the USSR absolutely.
могли спокойно уехать из СССР абсолютно
So, in fact, more people came to us
Так к нам вообще-то больше
in England. Workers carried out strikes
ехало в Англии Стачки рабочие проводили
We want the same working conditions as
Мы хотим такие же условия труда Как как
in Socialist
и в Социалистической
Russia, but
России а
guys, I don’t understand, I’m now telling
ребята не я понимаю я сейчас рассказываю
things that are in my head, but they
вещи которые в голове а у меня они тоже
didn’t fit in my mind either, I spent one year
не укладывались я один год потратил на
studying, one last year studying
изучение один последний год на изучение
everything. That’s what I found the time.  and
всего Вот этого я я находил время Вот и
when I realized what I
когда я понял какой я
was like, well, excuse
был ну извините
me, wait, now I’ll pour it, let’s
я подождите сейчас я налью давай
We live in a total
Мы живём в тотальной
lie, so far
лжи так пока
Dimonchik
Димончик
has Dimon’s hole there. Who wants to continue
у Димона там нычка Кто хочет продолжение
the conversation with Dimon, drop Donat, otherwise we’ll
разговора с Димоном закиньте Донат а то
turn it off
отключим
[music]
[музыка]
Dimon's wife Or where from
Димона жены Или откуда
Uh
Ух
[music]
[музыка]
a second let's go while you're pouring this I'll
секунду давай пока ты это э наливаешь
ask the question When did
спрошу получается вопрос Когда в
people in the Soviet Union appear
Советском Союзе у людей появились
under
при
Khrushchev So how come they
хрущеве Так а как же они пристали не
couldn't go abroad without passports
могли выехать за границу без паспортов
Because under Stalin a citizen of
Потому что при Сталине у гражданина
the Soviet  The Union had the highest legal
Советского Союза был высший юридический
status, a
статус
person did not need a passport. But
человек ему паспорт не нужен был А вот
when traveling
при выезде за
abroad, only when traveling abroad. Yes,
границу только при выезде за границу Да
you need the beginning of the fifties.
начало пятидесятых ты
Ask me.  I agree yes Well there
Поинтересуйся Я согласен да Ну там
was poverty there yes Usually people in the Soviet Union for some reason
нищета была да Обычно люди почему-то в
all went to Siberia and not
Советском Союзе все ехали в Сибирь а не
to France for some reason
во Францию почему-то
why is this so
почему это так
interesting you are sitting like this in
интересно вот так сидишь ты да в
some Estonia or Latvia Lithuania and
какой-то там Эстонии Да Латвии Литве и
instead of going there  to
вместо того чтобы поехать там в
Finland or to Germany Yes, you went to
Финляндию или в Германию Да ты поехал в
Siberia in the camps,
Сибирь в лагерях все-то а кто
everyone is interested in everyone. I mean, who is
все-то интересно В смысле А кто
everyone? Listen, this is a question: Why
все-то Слушай а такой вопрос А почему в
were they taken to Stalin’s camps?  people together
сталинские лагеря забирали людей вместе
with children Even with
с детьми Даже с
children, Lord, where from I don’t
детьми Господи откуда отку не я
understand I understand
понимаю я понимаю на него
so much about him, how do you imagine it,
столько вот ты как себе это
bring them out and
вывести ещё и детей
keep their children there, feed them, and so there are
их там содержать кормить тож так есть
a lot of people who grew up in camps,
куча людей есть выросли в лагерях
wait, so maybe it’s easier right away, but what?  to
подожди Так а может Проще сразу а а что
take a steam bath Or maybe there are
париться А может там
children there, members of these families of enemies of the people
детей-то членов этих семей врагов народа
and not Well, look why why did they take the children
а не Ну смотри зачем зачем детей брали
Yes with us And so on, seven near
Да снами И так дальше семь бли
the camp So wait again, that is,
лагерь Так подожди ещё раз то есть
Some person in
Человек какой-либо находящийся на
any
какой-либо
position stole a socialist
должности украл социалистическую
public  property Yes, in the form of
общественную собственность Да в виде
money or something else Yes, and he,
денег виде либо ещё чего-либо Да и его
along with his wife and children, are packed up and
вместе с женой и детьми пакуют и
sent to a camp. Are you so-so, is
отправляют в лагерь Это ты так себе это
n’t that what you imagined? But for example, they
ли представ не то что А вот например
considered that he was an enemy of the people because he
посчитали что враг народа потому что он
said good things about America, for example
там про Америку хорошо сказал например
yes Or criticized the Soviet
да Или критиковал Советский
system and him and his wife and children Yes, they took him to the
строй и его и жену и детей Да взяли в
camp Do you know at least one of them? You know a lot of people like that, a lot of people like that,
лагерь А ты хоть одного Знаешь такого
yes, yes And
знакомых да да
you had a very good film made in Ukraine,
А у вас в Украине сняли очень хороший
what is your sixteenth or seventeenth
фильм какой шестнадцатый или семнадцатый
year?
год
the ordinary Ukrainian flag how lies work in Kyiv was taken down Yes, never trust the testimony of eyewitnesses Yes, they are those boxes And you hang your ears The existing industry of the Soviet Union was created under Stalin, this is the energy sector, first of all, then comes metallurgy And so on, the manufacturing industry that we have now it’s working, that is, it turns out I understand correctly, neither before Stalin nor after Stalin did they open Mines factories Where in tsarist Russia and in tsarist Russia and before  Stalin's USSR Well, there
России и в до сталинской СССР Ну
were some Mines in Tsarist Russia, I
какие-то Шахты были в царской России
understand, yes, some Mines
понял да какие-то Шахты и после Сталина
didn’t open anything after Stalin. Why, after
ничего не открывали Да почему же после
Stalin, especially oil was discovered. Okay,
Сталина открывали особенно нефть Ладно
next one, let’s then the oil pipeline,
следующий во давай потом нефтепровод
friendship And then Brezhnev came to power and
дружба А там Брежнев к власти пришёл а
then hope for the fuel crisis in  countries of
потом хоупа топливный кризис в странах
Western Europe and
Западной Европы и
America Christina look look Christina
Америки христин смотри смотри Христина
asks Is it possible to call a leader
спрашивает Можно ли назвать лидера
great if he was feared more than
великим если его больше боялись чем
loved or respected; a leader is
любили или уважали лидера
recognized as Great by his
великим признают за Великого по его
deeds and  not out of fear,
делам а не из-за боязни
we already mentioned North Korea here. Yes,
мы уже тут упоминали Северную Корею Да
look at the generals of North Korea.
ты посмотри на генералов Северной Кореи
And not with
А не вот
these, what do the stars have to do with them like this?
этими причём там звёзды вот такие вот
like they fled to the
которые от хорошей жизни типа бежали в
USSR Yes, they were sent to be shot at
СССР Да их отправляли на расстрел
US citizens who came to build the USSR Yes,
граждан США приехавших в строить СССР Да
almost everyone was imprisoned so that they would not leave, their
пересаж почти всех чтобы не уезжали
passports were taken away, this is what my relatives
отбирали паспорта это мои родственники
say
говорят
Yes, well  Well,
Да ну что
maybe, maybe, everything can
быть может быть Всё может
be. So okay, next questions Let's go Di
быть Так ладно дальше вопросы Давайте ди
Mon so
Мон так
wait I'll have a drink First, let's
подожди я выпью Сначала давай
Dima so that
Дима чтоб
Putin
Путин
let's Suren asks if you would like
давай Сурен спрашивает хотел ли бы ты
Saakashvili to become president of
чтобы Саакашвили стал президентом
Russia
России
yes yes he has brought order to Georgia
да да он в Грузии порядок
Yes if he has brought order to  Georgia, he
навёл Да если он нал порядок в Грузии он
will restore order in Russia, I understood the question. I
наведёт порядок в России понял э вопро Я
was sitting in a square with a
в каре сидел с
Georgian, and here you are, somehow,
грузином ты вот и у нас как-то ре зашла
for this, for those years, when I
вот за это за те года вот когда вот там
was there. And what do you want?  your
был А что вот вам что вот ваша
Propaganda says Yes, that’s all when
Пропаганда говорит Да это всё вот когда
Saakashvili came, Mikheil Yes, he introduced corruption,
пришёл Саакашвили Михаил Да он коррупцию
banditry, crime,
бандитизм криминал
I understand, I understand the question, you said I was
я понял Поня сри вопрос Ты сказал Я в
sitting in a cell with a Georgian, this is when
камере сидел с грузином это когда изза
you were in prison because of what Lina personally understood, Yes,
что ты сидел это лично понял Лине Да так
let’s go question Kristinka Good question
Поехали вопрос Кристинка Хороший вопрос
says how  you really, how is this in Russian,
говорит как вы правда как это по-русски
how to justify the deportation of entire peoples
как оправдать депортацию целых народов
during Stalin’s time, isn’t this
во время Сталина разве это не
genocide,
геноцид
deportation, deportation, for example, of the Crimean
депортацию депортация например Крымских
Tatars  yes yes
Татар да да
Yeah this is when German troops approached
Ага это когда немецкие войска подошли к
Crimea and no when they left Crimea already
Крыму и нет когда они вышли из Крыма уже
when they left Crimea Yes in what
когда они вышли из Крыма у Да в со чем
year was the deportation of the Crimean
году депортация Крымских
Tatars in 1944
Татар в сорок четвёртом году
So at that time Crimea had already been recaptured
Так в то время Крым уже отбили
Amy
Эми
Inter there are deportations of bad people
Интере есть депортации лых народо
Dear  Discord members, what do you
Уважаемые участники Дискорда вы что
think, I’m Fyodor Dvinyatin or something, I
думаете я Фёдор Двинятин что ли какой-то
know all the answers to the question No, that’s not
на все ответы вопрос знаю Нет это не
true, but I know something,
так но кое-что знаю
there’s a city  New York Yes, look, the
есть город ньюйорк Да смотри директор
director, look, the director of the distillery
директор смотри директор спиртзавода
asks a question, yes, that when they were
задаёт вопрос да такой что вот когда
declared enemies of the people, they were taken to
врагов народа объявляли их забирали в
camps, then the children were sent to orphanages as
лагеря то детей отправляли в детдома как
enemies of the
врагов
people. Well, they were deprived of all rights, everything is
народа Ну их лишали всех прав всё
correct. Why, why were the children deprived of
правильно А зачем почему детей лишали
all rights, yes? And I’ll explain. Why google it?
всех прав да А я объясню Зачем загугли
Googled Solovyov’s son Vladimir
загугли сын Соловьёва Владимира
in London, this is this with long
в Лондоне вот это вот с длинными
hair, this is this and And what does it mean under
волосиками вот это вот и А причём при
Stalin, look, they announced  someone friend
Сталине смотри объявили кого-то другом
Naro googled the son of Vladimir Solovyov
Наро загугли сын Владимира Соловьёва
googled What do you think Dear
загугли Как ты думаешь Уважаемый
questioner This is what needs to be done with him
задающий вопрос Вот что с ним делать
And and not only with him,
А а и не только с ним
that is, look, I understand correctly that
то есть смотри я правильно понимаю что
you think that under Stalin it was
ты считаешь что при Сталине было
normal that if someone was declared  an
нормально что если кто-то был объявлен
enemy of the people, and then his children were sent
врагом народа да то его детей отправляли
to their
в
grandfather. Well, if mom and dad were sent to
дедом Ну если маму папу отправили в
camps, why throw him out on the street?
лагеря что ж его на улицу выбрасывать
Well, you can give it to the grandmothers to some
что А ну можно отдать бабушкам каким-то
relatives, well, there are a lot of relatives
родственникам ж куча родственников
stuck no birth rate grew
пристали не рождаемость росла
relatives there was
родственников была
darkness Well, they gave it to the VM they gave it to
тьма Ну отдавали ВМ отдавали
the VM What
ВМ В чём
was the tragedy of such Makarenko worked from the
трагедия был такой Макаренко с
orphanage,
детдомовца
wonderful people grew up from
работал прекрасные люди выросли из
orphanages And how many people did not grow up
детдомов А сколько людей не выросло
normal from orphanages, but the crippled
нормальных из детдомов а искалеченных
remained
остались
crippled, oh, just crippled
искалеченных да ой прямо уж искалеченных
that they were taken away from normal life from
что Их забрали из нормальной жизни от
parents Yes, the parents sent them to camps
родителей Да родители отправили в лагеря
and to their grandfathers, but the children will have science, which is not
и в дедом а же детям наука будет что не
necessary, like their parents, look again  Well,
надо как их родители ещё раз смотри ну
the child is not responsible for the father for the mother,
ребёнок не отвечает за отца за мать с
why on earth with the
какой стати с
legal one? What are you saying?
юридической с юридической Да ты
Read the documents, the falsity of the world 370 years
что Почитай документы фальс мира 370 лет
ago they even tried the dead and struck down
назад судили мёртвых даже и поражали во
their children with all the rights if someone violated
всех правах их детей если кто-то нарушал
the rules of the
правила
Peace of Westphalia 300 something years ago
вестфальский мир 300 С чем-то лет назад
I advise you to take an interest in the dacha, look, I
даче советую поинтересоваться смотри я
advise you, the whole modern world lives by these rules, I
тебе советую по этим правим живёт весь
advise those Ponte people
мир советую те понте
also seized
ещ захватили
power and said, but here we are now
власть и сказали а вот мы теперь тут
owners, what to do with them, that
хозяева что с ними делать
is, look, the question turns out, look, it
то есть смотри получается вопрос смотри
turns out that such a thing is that you are sending that
получается такая штука что ты шлёшь что
something is folded
что-то ви сфальцованный
correctly so that it is disgraceful to
правильно чтоб неповадно было
others. How else can you understand people, people, at
другим А как иначе ты пойми люди люди по
their core, are animals and only 10% of the
своей сути это животное и только 10% из
total population of this planet are  go
общего населения этой планеты они идут
against nature animal and They behave
против природы животный и Они ведут себя
like
как
people human I strive for man
люди человеком Я стремлюсь к человеку
understood good sincere answer So okay
понял хороший искренний ответ Так ладно
next questions let's do
следующие вопросы давайте
this Christian asks Why were
так христин спрашивает Почему
scientists and
репрессировали учёных и
officers of scientists repressed  Let's start with scientists
офицеров учёных Давайте начнём с учёных
Let's patent
Давайте патентное
law You know, there is such a thing as a
право Знаете есть такая штука
patent,
патент
in the twenties and thirties,
вот в двадцатые тридцатые го были
universities, institutes,
университеты институты
laboratories were created, the very first laboratory
лаборатории самая первая лаборатория
appeared in the eighteenth year, the
появилась в восемнадцатом году
Nizhny Novgorod laboratory, Bonch Bruevich
Нижегородская лаборатория Бонч бруевич
was the organizer of the Bolshevik, by the way, what did they
был организатор Большевик кстати чем они
do with radio communications and
занимались радиосвязью и
broadcasting,
радиовещанием
and then the development of
да потом появилось развитие
science appeared from the end  twenties and early
науки с конца двадцатых и По началу
thirties Yes, something natural.
тридцатых Да что-то из естественно
Naturally, they invented something,
Естественно что-то изобретали что-то
they came up with something because, well, here in this
придумывали потому что ну здесь на этой
territory the people have such a climate here
территории народ такой здесь климат
cold here 7 months the mother of his
холодный здесь 7 месяцев мать его
cold months of the year Here he is sitting at
холодных месяцев в году Вот он сидит
home he has something to do Here I am
дома ему делать он что-то Вот как я вот
sitting here
что-то сижу
inventing something in the evening I drink whiskey before going to bed By the way, it’s time for me to
изобретают вечер Пью виски перед сном
sleep
мне кстати спать уже пора
I didn’t answer the question let’s answer
вопро я не ответил на давай отвечай
quickly
быстрее
that’s why they were repressed  scientists and which
вот Почему репрессировали учёных а каких
scientists did you repress? Those who
учёных ты репрессировали те кто в
transferred scientific inventions to Switzerland
Швейцарию научные изобретения передавал
and patented them there And you are
и которые там патентовать А вы
interested in the loss for their ZM segment in RuNet, in
ЗМ сегменте в рунете интересуйтесь вы на
English via VPN Yes  type
английском языке через ВПН Да наберите
a request and you will get all the information You
запрос и вы получите всю информацию Ты
won’t believe it in English you can
не поверишь на английском языке можно и
type
без VPN набирать
requests in Los Angeles without a VPN, yes But in
запросы в лос-анджелесе да А вот в
Yekaterinburg
Екатеринбурге
No, without English letters don’t work
Нет без не работают английские
English letters don’t
буквы английские буквы работают не
work search for information is necessary Yeah,
работает поиск информации нужно Угу
because in RuNet everything
потому что в рунете всё
starts with the question  about Korolev Korolev was
зачином вопрос про Королёва Королёв был
repressed, yes he was for what, how for what,
репрессирован да был за что как за что
they from a group of scientists transferred these
они с группы учёных передавали данные
inventions to Switzerland, he
свои изобретения опять же в Швейцарию он
was engaged in Not only  rocket science, but also
занимался Не только ракетостроения но и
aircraft
самолётной
technology, he was repressed and did the right thing,
техникой его репрессировали и правильно
but When the
но Когда возникла
need arose When the need arose, do you hear
нужда Когда возникла нужда слышишь
Korolev, you were working on rockets here, but
Королёв ты тут это ракетами занимался но
no, but we didn’t have any other scientists there, there
нет у нас но не было там других учёных
weren’t any others, but they transplanted everyone, and
не было других по пересадили всех да и
Well, no one shot the cow, well  didn’t
Ну корова-то никто не расстреливал ну не
have time Yes, they pulled him out of prison then so
успели Да вытянули из тюрьмы потом так
well. In the sense that they pulled him out, they pulled him into a
хорошо В смысле вытянули его вытянули в
closed boarding house
закрытый пансионат
into a closed one, I understood. So where did he and his
в закрытый понял Так где он со своей
Group write repressed Nikolai
Груп пишут репрессировали Николая
Vavilov, a world-famous scientist, the same
Вавилова учёного с мировыми именем та же
story is that he sold the Swiss to
история что он швейцарца
transfer valuable information abroad
продавал передача за рубеж ценных
Uh-huh Evgeniy Asks You can
Угу Евгений Спрашивает Вы можете
count in English to
посчитать по английски до
20 today, try it Come on,
20 ни сегодня попробуй Давай
try it, come on Jump on one leg,
попробуй а давай Попрыгай на одной ноге
not for us It’s interesting for us, it’s interesting, you
не нам Интересно нам интересно вот
know this approximately  from the
примерно знаешь это вот примерно из той
same opera Come on, you jumped on one leg
же оперы А давай ты на одной ноге
20 times, I won’t jump on
попрыгали 20 раз я не буду прыгать на
one leg 20 times,
одной ноге 20 раз
yes. Ksenia correctly writes how  these
да Во Ксения правильно пишет как эти
Swiss scientists transferred their
учёные швейцарца передавали свои
technologies by postal government agents
технологии почтовыми гоз агентов
open or
открытые ни
agents
агенты
understood there was free entry and free
понял был свободный въезд и свободный
exit understood
выезд понял
so guys you know very little about the
так ребята Вы очень мало знаете об
history of our
истории нашей
country spend the same amount of time as
страны потратьте столько же времени
me just a year Frick writes
сколько и я всего год Фрик пишет коро
Korolev's jaw
королёву челюсть пытками
was broken by torture I have no
сломали я без
idea Well
понятия Ну может
maybe the queen’s jaw was broken by torture
быть а королёву челюсть пытками сломали
Yes, how
Да как
interesting But
интересно А вот
look here we had such a comrade
смотри тут у нас был такой товарищ
Serdyukov, yes yes at one
Сердюков да да одно
time Which one is from the Ministry of Defense
время Который из Министерства обороны
miles you have modern  I’m not
мили у вас современная Россия это мне не
interested in Russia, I’m interested in history, you’re
интересно мне по истории интересно ты по
rummaging through Stalin, modern
Сталину шаришь современная
me for
ме на протяжении
centuries People don’t change, look,
веков Люди не меняются вот смотри вот он
Serdyukov stole billions, yes And what can
Сердюков украл миллиарды да А что может
break his jaw so that he can
ему челюсть сломать чтобы он номера
reveal the numbers of Swiss banks where these
швейцарских банков открыл где Эти
billions are? And he’s just
миллиарды лежат А а а его просто на
they transferred to another position, but who
другую должность перевели а а кому же
would be better off with a jaw, and
этому правильнее было бы челюсть а
look about Korolev, so I read it like
смотри про Королёва вот я читаю
this,
так
means Korolev was arrested 37 years
значит Королёв был арестован так 37 года
after Ivan’s arrest  Klemenov and other
после ареста Ивана Клеменова и других
workers of the reactive institute, the arrest of
работников реактивного института арест
Korolev authorized the act, the
Королёва санкционировал акта
resolution
постановление
signed the basis for the arrest, wait, the
подписал основание для ареста подожди
grounds for the arrest were
вот основаниями для ареста являлись
the testimony of those arrested in the wound of Ivan Klem
показания арестованных ране Ивана Клем
Georgy, all three called Korolev an
георги гма все трое называли Королёва
accomplice of a certain counter-revolutionary
соучастником некой контрреволюционной
organization within the Russian Federation, whose
Троцкий организации внутри ры ставящее
goal was to weaken the defense power
своей целью ослабление оборонной мощи в
for the sake of
угоду
fascism under I  so on Yes, well,
фашизму поде И так дальше Да ну
in short,
короче
Lord, listen, let’s take away our point of view on this issue.
Господи Слушай давай к этому вопросу отм
Yes,  look, you are
сло точки зрения Да вот смотри ты
the head of a research
руководитель научно-исследовательского
institute, yes, you are making breakthrough
института Да ты делаешь прорывные
discoveries in jet rocketry,
открытия в реактивном ракетостроении
aircraft manufacturing, yes, breakthrough discoveries that
самолётостроении Да прорывные у которых
no one has, not like Switzerland in
нет ни у кого не то что у Швейцарии в
Germany, in London, in England, yes, no one
Германии в Лондоне в Англии Да ни у кого
has And then
нет И тут
wait for the transfer of the post
жди перева поста тро
in some  bar or restaurant Yes,
в какой-нибудь барчик или ресторанчик Да
and then such a man comes up to him,
и тут подходит к нему Такой мужчина
so well dressed in a hat and tie
такой хорошо одетый в шляпе в галстуке
Yes, and he says Listen, Comrade
Да и говорит Слушай говорит товарищ
Korolev says, here comrades are interested there in
Королёв тут товарищи интересуются там в
other countries Yes, he opens it for him  what and the
других странах Да открывает ему чемо а
circulation of currency under Stalin was completely
хождение валюты при Сталине было вполне
legal for currency only under the Khru they began
законным за валюту только при хру стали
to punish and imprison
наказывать и сажать
Well, look at the question about Korolev No,
Ну смотри вопро про Королёва Не не
wait, No, no, I want No, I want that,
подожди Не не нет я хочу Нет я хочу это
I won’t tell you now, I’m clearly talking about
я теб сейчас не буду я те чётко про
Korolev, look, I’ll take the jaw or else  that
Королёва смотри приму челюсть не то что
they just gouged it out there, in short,
раздолбили там просто короче вообще
look at all. Therefore, it took 5
смотри Следовательно потребовалось 5
weeks to extract the testimony they needed from Korolev,
недель чтобы выбить из Королёва нужный
he was accused of being an enemy of the people, he
им показания его обвинили врагом народа
was kept in  in solitary confinement, they broke
держали в одиночной камере сломали
their jaw, they threatened to arrest their wife and
челюсть угрожали арестом жены и
send their daughter to an orphanage, and so
отправкой дочери в детский дом и так
on, this
дальше этот
suitcase is natural.
чемоданчик естественно
Well, people, they are
Ну люди они
unteachable, if you were there, would you be the
необучаемых бы там был ты был бы
king of Tupolev or I don’t know,
королёвым Туполево или я не знаю там
Einstein there? Yes, people always want
эйнштейном Да люди всегда хотят что
money, wealth, to eat and drink. Good
деньги богатство жрать и пить Хорошо
question question.  interesting Yes, people all over the
вопрос вопрос интересный Да люди во всём
world are the same, so the absolute question is
мире одинаковы так абсолютно вопрос
why then did people in the USSR need to
почему тогда люди в СССР нужно их было
repress their children in orphanages and in
репрессировать ихних детей в детдома а
Britain in the USA in France and in other
Британии в США во Франции и в других
countries? Yes, these did not exist  repressions of
странах Да не было вот этих репрессий
camps such as orphanages and somehow they
лагерей типа детдомов да и как-то
developed
развивались
developed Oh how interesting
развивались Ой как интересно
they developed And how did they develop in the
развивались А как же они развивались
fifties sixties seventies well
пятидесятые шестидесятые семидесятые
somehow developed No somehow
года ну как-то развивались Нет как-то
somehow they began to develop after this
как-то они стали развиваться после сеь
year Well, look at the atomic bomb
года Ну как смотрите атомную бомбу
for the first time Americans yes  like not
впервые американцы да типа не
American Well, well, they used American
Американ Ну вот ну использовали Американ
That is, it turns out somehow They look without
То есть получается как-то Они смотри без
repression Yes, without grandfathers they somehow managed to
репрессий Да без дедов как-то смогли
develop an atomic bomb Yes no no the
разработать атомную бомбу Да нет нет
last military battles of
последние военные сражения Второй
World War II  did not take place in Berlin. But
мировой войны происходили не в Берлине А
in
в
Czechoslovakia, you know
Чехословакии знаешь
why, because there
почему потому что там урановые
were uranium deposits and centrifuges that were
месторождения были и центрифуги которые
enriched with uranium. There were also things that the
обогащённые Уран на
Americans captured that
Бывали и то что захватили американцы
were enough for exactly two bombs. The technology for
хватило ровно на две бомбы технология
producing an atomic bomb is simple to the point of
производства атомной бомбы проста до
disgrace. There you just need very,
безобразия Там просто нужен обо очень
very highly enriched uranium, which
очень сильно обогащённый Уран который
is  so it collapses very quickly, yes,
вот так вот схлопывается Очень быстро да
and there’s a sound around the sphere that still
И вокруг сфера со звучат которая его ещ
squeezes it like that, and then a
вот так вот сжимает а потом происходит
chain
Цепная
reaction happens, that’s how any schoolchild knows,
реакция всё так это любой школьник знает
well  at least my years of
Ну по крайней мере моих годов
production
выпуска
Yes, the whole problem was in the extraction of
Да вся проблема была в добыче
Uranium, the Americans got this Uranium for
Урана американцы этот Уран
exactly two bombs that they
получили ровно на две бомбы которые они
dropped. And how did they get it if
сбросили А как они получили если в
there were Soviet troops in Czechoslovakia and not
Чехословакии были советские войска а не
American ones? Not only were Soviet troops there, and American troops
войска были там и американские войска
were there and fought  by the way, another
были и дрались они вот кстати Ещё одна
secret history of the Second World
засекреченная история Второй мировой
War. What happened in Czechoslovakia in
войны Что происходило в Чехословакии в
early May of 1945, who fought for
начале мая сорок пятого года что кто за
what,
что
for the uranium mines, not the
боролся за урановые рудники не
mines, but what these
рудники а то что производили эти
uranium mines produced  Springs enriched uranium
урановые Родники обогащённый Уран
enriched uranium It’s absolutely true that
обогащённый Уран Совершенно верно
uranium beans were dropped on Hiroshima and Nagasaki, the plutonium was received
урановые бобы плутоний получили
much later in the sixties. That
значительно позже в шестидесятые годы То
is, it turns out that
есть получается на Хиросиму Нагасаки
Czechoslovakian uranium was dropped on Hiroshima Nagasaki yes yes Listen,
скинули чехословацкий Уран да да Слушай
but I can’t I look at the map and how did the
а вот я не могу Я по карте смотрю да как
German troops get into  Czechoslovakia
же немецкие войска попали в Чехословакию
if Ukraine is coming, but Ukraine, that
если вот идёт Украина Да вот Украина то
is, the Soviet Union was  Czechoslovakia And
есть Советский Союз был Чехословакия А
already in the East, the first thing that
по уже Восточная г первое что завоевали
Hitler’s troops conquered was Czechoslovakia How the
гитлеровские войска это Чехословакию Как
Americans got into Czechoslovakia Well, they
американцы попали в Чехословакию Ну они
got there in 1945, so look from there, the
попали то в сорок пятом так оттуда
Americans went from Normandy Well,
смотри американцы шли с Нормандии Да ну
from the west to Berlin, Soviet troops from
с запада на Берлин советские войска с
the east, Soviet troops passed
востока советские войска прошли
Czechoslovakia and entered Germany
Чехословакию и вошли в Германию
Eastern
Восточную
Americans to the Western How did the Americans
Американцы в западную Как американцы
pass through Soviet troops through East
прошли советские войска Восточную
Germany and end up in the Czechoslovaks?
Германии и попали в чехословаки средств
Were there no means of transportation or something?  at that
передвижения не было что ли в то
time, yes, just like the Soviet
время да точно так же как и советские
troops, look again, listen, just
войска ещё раз смотри слушай только не
don’t, this is this, this is this, this is this, this is this, this is this, this is
надо вот это вот вот это вот смотри вот
Berlin, this is Berlin, American troops
Берлин вот Берлин американские войска
are coming from here, Soviet troops are coming from here,
идут отсюда советские идут отсюда
passing through Czechoslovakia and Here they
проходят Чехословакию и Вот они тут в
are already fighting here in Berlin, like they’re fighting there  with
Берлине бьются уже да типа там бьются с
Hitler Yes, the Czechoslovakians are
Гитлером Да чехословацкие вот
there and Berlin was taken by May 2
там да Берлин был взят ко 2 мая
But Mary is here Maryan is now a Maryan from
А вот Маря тут Марьян сейчас марян из
Czechoslovakia Yes, interesting But
Чехословакии Да интересно А вот
interesting, Why Victory Day is the ninth and
интересно А почему День Победы девятае а
Niko look look I’m just curious
Нико смотри смотри мне просто интересно
Explain to me how the German troops through
Объясни мне как немецкие войска через
what country they got to Czechoslovakia
какую страну они попали в Чехословакию
Lord through
Господи через
Austria You never know how they could
Австрию Да мало ли как они могли там
get there They were already there in the early
попасть Они были уже там уже в начале
forties in Czechoslovakia they were already
сороковых в Чехословакии они уже тогда в
developing an atomic
начале сороковых разрабатывали атомную
bomb in the early forties the Americans would  Germans Yes, I'm like
бомбу американцы бы немцы Да я как
Americans, they're Germans It's clear How the
американцы это немцы Понятно Как
Americans got to
американцы попали в
Czechoslovakia, just don't get lost, you
Чехословакию только не пропадай ты тоже
don't get lost either I'm already here, I'm here, I'm here, I
не пропадай Я уже тут я тут я тут всё я
'm back How the Americans got there  to
вернулся Как американцы попали в
Czechoslovakia in 1945. Yes,
Чехословакию в сорок пятом Да
basically no one bothered them at that time.
элементарно им в то время уже тогда
Well, all the German troops were defeated,
мешал Ну всё немецкие войска разбиты всё
the surrender was signed on May 2, so the
капитуляция была подписана 2 мая так
Soviet troops marched through Czechoslovakia,
советские войска прошли по Чехословакии
Czechoslovakia was completely under the control of the Soviet troops.
была Чехословакия
Well, maybe so. Okay, Dean, a serious
Ну ну может быть так Ладно Дин серьёзный
question, how  do you feel about the existence of the
вопрос как ты относишься к существовании
possible existence of extraterrestrial
к возможному существованию внеземных
civilizations I have never seen If I don’t
цивилизаций никогда не видел Если сам не
see it myself I won’t believe it I understand how you think
увижу не поверю понял как ты считаешь
Earth Circle silt
Земля Круг ило
but look, just go out into the yard, it’s
но выглядите выйдите просто во двор она
round Well, it’s round, yes Well, maybe it’s
круглая Ну круглая да Ну может она
flat We can’t see it because it’s
плоская Мы же не видим вот так как она
illuminated at the edges And so on Yes,
подсвечивается по краям И так дальше Да
it can’t be flat Well, look at
она не может быть плоской Ну смотри В
all sorts of things Yuri Loza Yes,
всякие там Юрий Лоза Да
which countrymen
которые ка земельки
are coming I’m the one  Most of all I hate
идут Я вот кого больше всего ненавижу
these obscurantists
это мракобесов
who brains people
которые мозги людям
understand who Rurik is,
понял кто такой Рюрик
you know Rurik is the first
знаешь Рюрик это первоя
dynasty of the kings of
династия царей
Muscovy, Muscovy,
московии московии
that's how We all know  Ivan I, that is,
вот как Мы все знаем Иван I то есть
the Terrible Yes, he began the
Грозный Да начал
expansion of this Muscovy about Inter so
расширение этой московии про Интере так
well, the question of code
рошо вопро кода
Well, long before Ivan
Ну задолго до Ивана
the Terrible, when actually Russian is an
Грозного когда вообще-то русский это
adjective, I understand, yes, this is not
прилагательно я понимаю да это не
an essence, it is an adjective Let me have a drink, Let
сущность это прилагательно Давай я выпью
me drink it with
Давай так а мне запить то есть
something, that is, wait for me
чем так подожди я
now the last question, what do you think,
сейчас последний вопрос что ты думаеш
check
прови
the wiring Okay, I’ll drink even without drinking.
разводка Ладно я даже без запивки выпью
I’ve already drunk enough. That’s it, let me
Я уже достаточно выпил Всё давай я
just
короче
run. Well,
побегу Ну
I was very glad  communicate with a smart
что я очень рад был пообщаться с умным
person because here in chat
человеком потому что тут в чат
roulette it’s just like
рулетке такая вообще
this I hope we’ll see each other again Let
это я надеюсь мы ещё увидимся Давай
me study the issue of the Finnish war let me
я поиз уча вопрос финской войны давай
study while I go I went
учать пока я пошл я пошёл
about fly agarics today I gave out the historical
о мухоморчики сегодня выдал исторический
context like squeak comment for the fact that I
контекст лайк писка комент за то что я
endured it all  subscribe to th Telegram
это всё выдержал подпишись на й Telegram
right now autumn and
прямо зараз осень а
pok tse more and more respectfully YouTube
пок це дуже и дуже важливо YouTube
driving us through Scar Georg  your ban and
загоняя нас через Скар Георг твый бан и
a lot of video I don’t show people right now I do
дуже багато вдео не показую людям вчасно
n’t show information about streams
не показуе информация про стримы тому
for this purpose for Mali operational link
для того щоб ми Мали оперативный звязок
to write directly in the meantime in telegra
пишиться прямо зараз а пок там в телегра
okm vdeo tej Tsikava and Korisna
окм вдео ще теж цикава и корисна
information and I’m sorry for you trimati
информация и ми повинни з вами тримати
fast operational link
постный оперативный звязок
independent in  I'll show you about Tsei
незалежно в того покаже вам про Цей
YouTube Glory to Ukraine  subscribe
YouTube Слава Украине подпишись